+91-8861349278

Mohammad A Rahman

Oracle Database Architect, Exadata DB, Golden Gate Specialist, PostgreSQL DBA, Cloud Solution Architect

SUMMARY

I am an IT professional with 16 years of total experience, including 11 years as a database administrator, architect, database replication specialist, and migration expert. I have extensive expertise across various domains such as healthcare, manufacturing; finance, telecom, and retail, and working in culturally diverse environments at multinational companies. My projects span technologies such as Oracle Database, PostgreSQL, Oracle Golden Gate, and AWS/OCI Cloud services. I utilize a range of tools for monitoring and performance tuning, including OEM, Oracle Veridata, PGAdmin, Datadog, PG extensions, and Cloud EC2, RDS, storage, networking include Route 53 or other services

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

- Oracle Database configuration, up-gradation, Migration, and performance tuning, includes multitenant, RAC database.
- > Provide high available from SOPF include disk level to instance level or service, and minimize IO wait.
- > Oracle Golden Gate replication include active-active, Data guard include FSFO, and also engage in migration.
- > Databases migrate from on-premises to OCI, AWS EC2 or RDS services and experiencing GCP Cloud services.
- RMAN backup recoveries to keep upgrade script handle to all kind of database outage.
- OEM target discovers, promotion, monitoring with AWR report analysis and online patching
- > PostgresSQL Database administrates backup recovery logical/ PITR, tuning, optimization, audit recommendation, and fix bug.
- Migrate on premise Oracle Database 11g to AWS RDS Aurora PostgreSQL, by initial load with cloud replication services.
- System administration and performance skills for Linux operative system includes Shell and Python scripting.

TECHNOLOGIES

- Oracle Database 10g/11g/12/19c, multitenant database on RAC/ non-RAC or super cluster environment.
- Database replication technologies like Oracle Data guard, Golden Gate, Veridata, and Backup recovery.
- PostgreSQL Database technologies like Aurora, HA Replication, Failover, Load Balancing and connection pooling.
- Cloud infra EC2, RDS, RDSADMIN, bucket, network, route table, Route 53, Cloud Front, Global accelerator, costing, and other services.
- SQL Developer, Toad, OEM 13c, DATADOG, JIRA Dashboard, and Remedy ticketing tools.
- > UNIX (AIX, HP-UX, Solaris), Linux (Red Hat) platform, and language SQL, PLSQL, Shell and Python

Education and Certification

- Master in Computer Application (MCA)
- ❖ AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate (SAA-C03)
- Oracle Database Administrator Certified Professional (OCP)
- Oracle Database Administrator Certified Associate (OCA)
- Oracle Database Certified SQL Expert

Work Experience	
Working as a Database Architect with Virtusa Private Limited	Nov 2020 to Present
Worked as a Database Architect with Collabera Technologies Private Limited Oct 2019 to July 2020	
Worked as a Senior Database Administrator with NTTDATA AUG -19 to SEPT 2019	
Worked as a Senior Database Administrator with IBM India PVT Ltd April 2017 to JAN 2019	
Worked as Oracle Application DBA with Primus Global Solution Ltd MAR 2015 to MAR 2017	
Worked as a Consultant with Apps Associates	Jun 2014 to Aug2014
Worked as an Oracle Golden Gate DBA with Envision Enterprise Solution Oct2012 to Jan2014.	
Worked as an Oracle Database Administrator with Introlligent Solutions PVT Ltd.	May 2011 to Aug 2012

Worked as a Healthcare Business Analyst with IBM Daksh Pvt. Ltd. Jan 2008 to J	
Worked as a Medical Analyst with Globerian India Pvt. Ltd May 2006 to May 2007	
Worked as a MIS executive with Matrix Processing House Jun 2005 to May 2006	

WORK EXPERIENCE and PROJECT COMPLETION

British Telecom – Cloud	Migration and DB Replication (Nov 2020 — Present)
Role	Database Architect
Technology	Oracle 11g, and Multitenant 12/19c, OEM, Golden Gate, PostgresSQL and AWS/GCP Cloud infra
Description	Development & Migration databases to Cloud Environments
Responsibilities	Complete SDLC for database up gradation and migration to 19c OEL 8 server along with maintenance procedures, documentation and ensure standards definition, security, and integrity. Configure and Oracle Data guard to switchover on new machine, Configure Golden gate for minimal migration downtime and replace standby server. Migrate on-premises databases to AWS EC2 customise machine or RDS database. Migrate AWS Oracle RDS database to open-source PostgresSQL database.DBA support and CR/SR request to apply require change to enhance performance. Planning for Production Storage and Capacity Management include Backup and Recovery including Pg_dump, pg_dumpall, setting up WAL archiving, Point in time recovery, including HA/DR Setup including logical, physical standby
INTUIT – Cloud Migration	n- Finance — Oct 2019 to Jul 2020
Role	Database Architect
Technology	Oracle Database 10/11g, 12/19c, OEM, Golden Gate, PostgreSQL Database, Cassandra NoSQL Database, Amazon Redshift database, AWS Cloud services, Storage, EC2, RDS, network Route 53 Cloud Front, Global accelerator and other services.
Description	Development & Migration databases to AWS Cloud Environment
Responsibilities	Lead support role for BMR migration and coordinate multiple scrum teams. Install/configure, upgradation, migration to 19c DB on two nodes cluster Linux machine and Golden Gate replication along with configure Oracle Veridata jobs for handle data sync issue and validation report Build active standby database upgrade version 19c on AWS Cloud EC2. AWS services to apps traffic control, Improve application scalability, high transfer speed with low latency or optimization. Creation, managing and migrating PostgreSQL schema, tables, tablespaces and users, roles and group include Planning for Production Storage and Capacity Management.

NTTDATA – Cloud Migration – Healthcare – AUG2019 – SEPT2019	
Role	Senior Database Administrator
Technology	Oracle 10/11g, 18c automated DB, RMAN, DATAPUMP and Oracle Cloud Infra(OCI)
Description	Migrate DB from on-premises to Oracle Cloud infrastructure
Responsibilities	Configured virtual machine on OCI and install, configured 11g database. RMAN backup script to run 10g DB and copy backup files to Storage Object. And build 11g database with backup & restoration on OCI platform. Lift & Shift assignment to schedule DATAPUM and Incremental backup scripts to schedule to take Backup & restore 18c DB. Support end to end migration SDLC and keep application process up and running with minimal downtime to complete migration before SLA.

Shop Direct Group-IBM Cloud Migration Retail – APRIL2017 to JAN 2019	
Role	Senior Database Administrator
Technology	Oracle 10/11g, 12c, SQL Server Database, Golden Gate, Veri-data, Linux, AWS Cloud Infra, JIRA
Description	Migrate application databases and provide POC for data lacking issues.

Responsibilities	Perform standard maintenance, administrative, PT statistics, and recommend corrective actions include backup recovery, up-gradation, migrate on-premise database to AWS EC2 servers as well RDS instances, and Golden Gate installation, configuration, tuning replication process. RAC databases support and validate cluster sync issue and OCR backup recovery. RMAN scripts and
	implementation Lo/L1/Archive backup according to SLA. Backup to Cloud storage and refresh require database on EC2 machine. Onsite client location to bring all data ingestion tasks request on JIRA application and improved dashboard tagging for workflow transparency

Wipro Technology — Baxter — Healthcare — NOV2016 to MAR2017	
Role	Senior Database Administrator
Technology	Oracle DB12c EM 13c Cloud Control on Exa-Data X4-2 machine
Description	Migrate Database to Cloud Control and Exadata admin
Responsibilities	OEM cloud control, target promotion, migration, maintenance and support. Support to cell server issue and patching all component of ExaData machine. Patch QFSDP which include Infini-Band switch, compute node, cell servers. Exadata Cell administration, database manages with cloud control (EM).

IBM – AT & T – Telecom – MAR 2015 to OCT 2016	
Role	Oracle Apps DBA
Technology	Oracle DB 10/11g/12c, RAC, Golden Gate, MongoDB, SQL Server and Micro-Service
Description	Migrate DBs to Oracle new version machine and Goldengate configuration
Responsibilities	Migrate DB from window & Linux platform to standard Linux Cloud environment. Mapping data transformation in Oracle Benchmark tool application specifications. Migrate SQL server to Oracle database using Oracle benchmark tool. Migrate the Oracle old version of DB to Oracle 12c database on 8-RAC nodes. Goldengate setup end to end for migration and configure for recovery filter data. Goldengate configured for unidirectional and bidirectional replication and reverse replication to old server for monitoring or rollback or others application testing. DB performance tuning, repair dead locks, and others user management roles. Documentation for business transformation.

Magma Fincorp — Finance— SEPT 2014 to FEB 2015	
Role	Consultant
Technology	Oracle 11g DB, RAC, X2-X4 Exadata with HP-Linux (2 nodes) and Golden Gate
Description	Migrate databases from non-RAC environments to Exadata 2-node RAC platform.
Responsibilities	POC and documentation for migration plan with zero downtime. Cross platform Database migration by using Golden Gate. Initial load to Goldengate with minimum downtime with high available for apps.

Apps Associate – IKEA – JAN 2014 to AUG 2014	
Role	Consultant
Technology	Oracle 10/11g, Golden Gate, Veridata, E-Business Suite 12.1, SOA 11g, and Fusion Applications
Description	Database replication and integration
Responsibilities	Configure Oracle Golden Gate on heterogeneous environment for DML replication. Implemented Oracle Golden Gate Veri-data for heterogeneous environment. Involved in all database support, maintenance and documentation.

Walgreens – ETL & Data movement – OCT 2012 to JAN 2014	
Role	Oracle Golden Gate DBA
Technology	Oracle 10/11g, Golden Gate, JMS Queues, Flat Files integration, RAC 2-nodes, and NAS share storage.
Description	Database replication and integration
Responsibilities	Golden Gate technical support for numbers of applications. Supporting replication for both DDL and DML operation. Implemented extract, filter and pump process for customized projects. Implemented data integration for Real-time Data Warehousing. Implemented initial data load to real time data integration. Configure the extract, pump, replicate and flat file writer process GG setup for ad-hoc request for restores recovery the data. Participate in CAB meetings and support decisions on represented change request. Handle all priorities tickets includes incident and change management. Documenting event logs, daily diary, handbook mapping excel sheet

Apple Inc. — Manufacture Quality Management (MQM)—MAY 2011 to AUG 2012	
Role	Oracle DBA
Technology	Oracle 10/11g, Grid, Golden Gate, Linux and Sun Solaris Exadata V2 / X2 (RAC 8-nodes), Toad, SQL Developer,
Description	Oracle Database Administrator
Responsibilities	Responsible for 24X7 support of production databases. Monitor database health check-up includes availability and connectivity with timely production issue remediation. Tune the databases performance, availability, growth report, event notifications, Applications statistics, Database statistics, OS statistics, define rules as per policy of each individual site, scheduling jobs. Managing database security and creating and assigning appropriate roles and privileges. Implemented table partitioning to improve performance and data management. Analyse tables on regular basis for Oracle optimizer, performed tuning and use explain plan, hint, indexing, and load balancing. Schedule the monitoring scripts for automation health check-up. Migrate databases to EXADATA Machines and manage DB on full RAC Exadata machine. Configured physical standby database during migration by using RMAN and backup. Using roll forward strategy on standby database sync issue when log corruption or other issues. Performed switchover when primary/secondary machine unstable. Configuration and scheduling logical, RMAN archive/incremental/full backups. Patch family— one off CPU, interim and BP12 patch. Toad/SQL developer tool for procedure compilation, generate scripts and application connection string test from client side. Using ASMCMD utility- dropping disk group, drop disk, add disk. Administrate ASM file access ontrol/directories/disk group templates/ASM performance. Golden gate troubleshooting and tuning included monitor ggserr.log, review check point details, evaluate process report; identifying bottlenecks such as lag, network issue, NFS access issue and tuning extraction, replication for optimal performance. Golden gate 11g troubleshooting and tuning included monitor ggserr.log, review check point details, evaluate process report, identifying bottlenecks such as lag, network issue, NFS access issue and tuning extraction, replication for optimal performance and resolving slow extraction, extract abends issues.

UHG — Healthcare Medical Insurance— Jan 2008 to Jun 2010	
Role	Healthcare Business Analyst
Technology	Oracle E-Business Application
Description	Health Care Medical coding and billing
Responsibilities	Proficiency with medical billing software and electronic health records (EHR). Focus on healthcare processes include emphasizes analyzing medical data, involving coding, Effective communication with patients, providers, and insurance agents. Familiarity with medical terminology related to diseases, treatments, anatomy, and physiology.